Guide to the University Council records, 1952-1962.
Duke University. University Archives
University Council records 1952-1962
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. University Council.
2.5 linear feet Extent: 2500 Items
The creation of the University Council was recommended by the General Faculty's Commission on Faculty Reorganization and authorized by the Board of Trustees in a 1952 revision of the University Bylaws. The collection contains original typed minutes, printed summary minutes, committee records and reports, correspondence, memoranda, agenda, rosters, election results, and other records ranging in date from 1952-1962.
UA.28.02.0002
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Provenance
The University Council records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1963, 1965, 1973.
Historical Note
The creation of the University Council was recommended by the General Faculty's Commission on Faculty Reorganization and authorized by the Board of Trustees in a 1952 revision of the University Bylaws. There were fifteen members, ten elected by the faculties of the various schools and colleges, and three appointed by the President. The President and the Vice President in the Educational Division (later the Provost) were members ex officio. There were three officers: the Chair, filled by the President, and a Vice Chair and Secretary, elected annually. The University Council was considered a standing committee of the Faculty and served as an advisory body on matters of general University policy and interest. It was intended to be a means by which the President could keep the Faculty informed of major policy matters, served as an investigative body, and tried to facilitate two-way communication between the Faculty and the Administration. It was supplanted by the Academic Council in 1962.
For histories and evaluations of the University Council. see R.L. Watson's "Report of the Vice Chairman to the University Council," May 23, 1962, and the Faculty and Duke Government: A Year on the University Council," by W. B. Hamilton (1961) located in box 3 below.
Collection Overview
The collection contains original typed minutes, printed summary minutes, committee records and reports, correspondence, memoranda, agenda, rosters, election results, and other records ranging in date from 1952-1962.
Major subjects include appointment, tenure and promotion policies, group life and medical insurance, tuition awards for faculty children, and other fringe benefits, the summer session, admission and grading standards, student life and government, and athletics and academics. Also of interest are reports and discussions about desegregation, the Gross-Edens affair, the format and function of the Academic Council, and the faculty's role in the selection of a president and in the revision of the University's Bylaws.
Subject Headings
Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. University Council; Duke University -- Faculty; College teachers -- North Carolina -- Durham; Faculty -- Congresses; Universities and colleges -- Faculty
Related Material
Preliminary Inventory of the A. Hollis Edens Records, 1949-1960.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Faculty Records, 1911-1986.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Richard L. Watson, Jr. Papers, 1941–1989.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Academic Council records, 1954-2000.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- University Council, 1952-1962, 5 Boxes
  - Minutes (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 11/52-6/54 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 10/554-5/56 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 10/56-5/59 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 10/59-12/60 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1/61-12/61 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, 1/62-5/62 (Box 1)
  - Committees (Box 2)
    - Report by Committee on Trends and Experiences in Desegregation at Universities in the South, 1955 (Box 2)
    - Buildings and Grounds, 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Faculty Organization, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Faculty Qualifications and Improvement, "The Selection, Retention, Promotion and…" 1962 (Box 2)
    - Faculty Committee on Bylaws, 1960-1962 (Box 2)
    - Committee on Fringe Benefits, 1954-1964 (Box 2)
    - Tuition Benefits (Box 2)
    - Reports (Duplicates) (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Minutes, Histories (Box 3)
    - History, "The Faculty and Duke Government: A Year on the University Council," W.B. Hamilton, 1961 (Box 3)
    - History, R.L. Watson, 1962 (Box 3)
    - History, "Proposals for the Establishment of a Faculty Senate, 1945-1946 (AAUP), Bylaws, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Summary Minutes, 1952-1958 (Box 3)
    - Summary Minutes, 1959-1962 (Box 3)
    - Agenda, Resolutions, etc… (Box 3)
    - Secretary and Vice Chair Correspondence, 1955-1962 (Box 3)
    - Memoranda, 1952-1962 (Box 3)
    - Rosters (Box 3)
    - Mailing Lists (Box 3)
    - Elections, 1952-1961 (Box 3)
  - Bylaws Committee (Box 4)
    - Chronology (Box 4)
    - Comparative Charts on Universities Organization (Box 4)
    - Chronological File, May-Sept. 1960 (Box 4)
    - Chronological File, Oct.-Dec. 1960 (Box 4)
    - Chronological File, Jan.-March 1961 (Box 4)
    - Chronological File, April-Dec. 1961 (Box 4)
    - Chronological File, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Office of the President, Administrative Study Committee Report, 16 December 1959 (Box 4)
    - Ratchford, B.U., "A Suggested Plan of Administrative Organization for Duke University," 11 January 1960 (Box 4)
    - Reports, Drafts, etc… (Duplicates) (Box 4)
  - Bylaws Committee (Box 5)
    - Bylaws, Charters, etc… (other schools), 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Ben Powell's Notes, 2 folders (Box 5)